Dr. Jochem H. Smit

Postdoctoral Researcher

jhsmit@gmail.com
jochem.smit@kuleuven.be

Nationality
Dutch
Date of Brith
23-09-1988

Summary My interest in mechanisms of physical law and biological machinery is what drives me to do research. I have a strong background in both Chemistry and Physics as well as programming proficiency which allows me to contribute to a broad range of interdisciplinary research projects.

Postdoctoral Training

2019–Present Rega Institute for Medical Research

KU Leuven

Established smFRET microscopy and developed software for the analysis of HDX-MS data at increased residue-level resolution.

Education

2015–2019 Phd Student

University of Groningen

PhD Thesis: Novel fluorescent probes and analysis methods for single-molecule and single-cell microscopy.

2010–2012 MSc Nanoscience

University of Groningen

Master Thesis: Organometallic Catalysis as seen by single molecule spectroscopy.

2007-2010

BSc Physics

University of Groningen

Bachelor Thesis: Synthesis of PTCDA derivatives and application of organic semiconductors in transistors. (shared thesis)

2006–2011

BSc Chemistry

University of Groningen

Bachelor Thesis: Synthesis of PTCDA derivatives and application of organic semiconductors in transistors. (shared thesis)

Publications

- **J. H. Smit**, ColiCoords: A Python package for analysis of rod-shaped single-cell fluorescence microscopy data in Jupyter notebooks. PLOS ONE **14**, e0217524
- **J. H. Smit**, J. H. M. van der Velde, J. Huang, V. Trauschke, S. Hendrikus, S. Chen, N. Eleftheriadis, E. M. Warszawik, C.M. Punter, A. Herrmann, T. Cordes, *On the impact of competing intra- and intermolecular triplet-state quenching on photobleaching and photoswitching kinetics of organic fluorophores. PCCP, 21, 3721-3733*
- J. H. M. van der Velde*, **J. H. Smit***, C.M. Punter, T. Cordes, *Self-healing dyes for super-resolution microscopy*. J. Phys. D: Appl. Phys, **52**, 034001
- 2018 E. M. Warszawik, J. H. Smit, Y. Li, M. Loznik, A. Paul, T. Cordes, A. Herrmann, *Uptake and Localization of Aminoglycoside Antibiotics in Live Escherichia Coli*. Biophysical Journal 114 (3), 629a

- J. Kim*, J. H. Smit*, D. K. Prusty, A. J. Musser, N. Tombros, P. C. W. Lee, A. Herrmann, M. Kwak, *Ultrasensitive Detection of Oligonucleotides: Single-Walled Carbon Nanotube Transistor Assembled by DNA Block Copolymer*. Journal of Nanoscience and Nanotechnology, 17 (8), 5175-5180
- J. H. M. van der Velde, J. Oelerich, J. Huang, J. H. Smit, A. A. Jazi, S. Galiani, K.l Kolmakov, G. Guoridis, C. Eggeling, A. Herrmann, G. Roelfes, T. Cordes, *A simple and versatile design concept for fluorophore derivatives with intramolecular photostabilization*. Nature Communications, 7, 10144
- J. H. M. van der Velde, J. Oelerich, J. Huang, J. H. Smit, M. Hiermaier, E. Ploetz, A. Herrmann, G. Roelfes, T. Cordes, *The power of two: covalent coupling of photostabilizers for fluorescence applications.* JPC Letters, **5** (21), 3792-3798
- 2012 I. Stein, S. Capone, J.H. Smit, F. Baumann, T. Cordes, P. Tinnefeld, Linking Single-Molecule Blinking to Chromophore Structure and Redox Potentials. ChemPhysChem, 13, 931-937

Research Experience

2013 Research Assistant

LMU Munich

Supervisor: Prof. Dr. Wolfgang Zinth

Keywords: Ultrafast Spectroscopy, Streak Camera, Time-resolved Fluorescence, Non-linear Optics

2012 Research Assistant

University of Groningen

Supervisor: Prof. Dr. T. Cordes

Keywords: Single-molecule Chemistry, Fluorescence Microscopy, Organopalladium Chemistry

2011 Internship

LMU Munich

Supervisor: Prof. Dr. P. Tinnefeld

Keywords: Confocal Microscopy, Photophysics, Single-molecule Studies, Redox Chemistry

2011 Internship

University of Groningen

Supervisor: Prof. Dr. A. Herrmann

Keywords: Graphene, Carbon Nanotubes, Organic Electronics, DNA Hybrid Materials, DNA Synthesis

Teaching

2015–2016 T.A. Thermodynamics

University of Groningen

Teaching of exercise classes Thermodynamics for 1st year physics students

Conferences

2018 Bacterial Protein Export

Leuven

Poster Presentation: *Uptake and Localization of Aminoglycoside Antibiotics in Live Escherichia Coli*

2018 PicoQuant Workshop

Rerlin

Oral Presentation: *Inter – vs intramolecular photostabilization of organic fluorophores*

2018	ology Oral Presentation: Uptake and Localization of Aminoglycoside Antiotics in Live Escherichia Coli	
2017	Zernike Institute for Advanced Materials meeting Vliela Oral Presentation: Inter- vs Intramolecular photostabilization of a ganic fluorophores	
2016	Dutch BioPhysics Poster Presentation: Design of photostabilizer-dye conjugates and of plications in super-resolution microscopy	
2015	PicoQuant Workshop Poster Presentation: The Power of Two: Covalent Coupling of Phostabilizers for Fluorescence Applications	
2015	Focus on Microscopy Oral Presentation: A Simple And Versatile Synthesis Strategy For tramolecular Photostabilization of Organic Fluorophores	•
	Fellowships and awards	
2018	FEMS Fellowship for attending BPE2018 conference	
2010–2012	Zernike Insitute for Advanced Materials Fellowship for TopMaster programme in Nanoscience	

Professional Affiliations

Member of the following societies:

- o Deutsche Physikalische Gesellschaft
- Nederlandse Natuurkunde Vereniging
- Biochemical Society
- o Koninklijke Nederlandse Vereniging voor Microbiologie